Alright, so welcome to the Scott Horton Show.
I am the Director of the Libertarian Institute Editorial Director of antiwar.com, author
of the book Fool's Arendt.
Time to end the war in Afghanistan and I've recorded more than 5,000 interviews going
back to 2003, all of which are available at scotthorton.org.
You can also sign up for the podcast feed.
The full archive is also available at youtube.com slash scotthorton show.
You guys on the line, I've got John Kiriakou.
He fought the terror wars for the CIA and then they put him in prison for confirming
the identity of some CIA torturers, the only person to be punished for George W.
Bush's torture program, you know, above officer level anyway, and certainly the only CIA officer
who was punished.
And now he's an antiwar guy, I think pretty much, fair to say, and writes great articles
about lots of important things.
Welcome back to the show, John.
How are you?
Thanks, doing well, thanks.
Good to talk to you again.
Yeah, man.
So, boy, there's a lot going on right now and you got this piece here, a terrible
take on the capital storming.
And that is in reference to a former associate of yours, former CIA officer Robert Grenier,
who readers of Fools' Air and will remember was the station chief in Islamabad at the
dawn of the terror war.
And he gave an interview to NPR News saying this and that about Al Qaeda and the Taliban
and the capital mob and the American right and some things.
And I wonder if you could explain a little bit here, maybe even read the quote if you've
got it about what it is he was getting at there.
You know what?
I'm going to pull up the quote.
What he talked about in an op-ed in the New York Times two weeks ago today, as a matter
of fact, was the fact that we need to treat events, insurrections, like we saw
on January the 6th here in Washington, as insurgencies.
And with insurgencies come counterinsurgencies.
And I said in my piece that, you know, I've known Grenier at all for a very long time
and what he means is we need to be killing people.
Well, killing people for what reason?
I say in my own piece that I was as sick and as everybody else was on January 6th.
I was as angry as everybody else was.
But we had a demonstration of some 15 or 20,000 people.
And we had, what, 500 to 800 that actually went inside the capital and were violent.
And most of them were unarmed.
I think that there are accounts of three people who we know definitively were armed.
And you're in the New York Times saying that we need to treat this as a counterinsurgency.
Now, what happens in counterinsurgencies is you go door to door and you bust down the door.
Sometimes you breach the door with explosives.
You grab everybody inside.
You zip tie them or cuff them.
You take them to some sort of an interrogation center and then you just sort it all out later.
Well, we've got this thing called a Constitution and you can't do stuff like that.
So, you know, in whatever little way that I could, Scott, I wanted to lay down a marker
and say this is wrong.
This is anti-American.
This is a violation of our constitutional rights.
And we've got to put a stop to it.
I was disgusted that the New York Times gave him a platform to even spout this nonsense.
Yeah.
You know, and I'm so sorry I've been so buried.
I got the new book out and everything.
I'm going to send you a copy.
I got enough now.
You're on the list.
What?
Thank you.
But...
Galatian.
I really...
Oh, thank you.
I appreciate that.
I hope you like it.
I'm pretty sure you will.
I know.
But...
Oh, I know.
So, my apology was I didn't even read the New York Times article and I forgot there
even was one.
I read in your piece that there was one, but I never got around to reading it.
I only read the NPR interview after the fact.
And then I just got stuck on this paragraph.
I just don't know what to do about it.
And here's what's so funny, John.
And, man, I can't wait to hear what you have to say about the giant mess of a question
I'm about to unload on you here, okay?
First of all, here it is.
She says, oh, so you were station chief in Islamabad on 9-11.
So what are the lessons from the war against al-Qaeda there?
And you know, me, I wrote the book about Afghanistan and I'm all hung up on this point.
And there's a part in the book where I talk about how Grineer had Grunye, whatever, had
organized with the Pakistanis to prevent friendly fire in case in the event that Bush allowed
Delta Force to chase after bin Laden when they crossed the border into Pakistan, which
never happened.
That's kind of part of the role he played there.
But anyway, and that's according to his book, 88 Days to Kandahar, where he writes about
all that.
But then it's so funny the way he says this, John, he goes, and yes, and you know, even
at the seeming height of the crisis immediately after 9-11, there really weren't that many
members of al-Qaeda in Afghanistan.
And the thrust of our campaign there was, yes, to hunt down al-Qaeda, but primarily to
remove the supportive environment in which they were able to live and to flourish.
And that meant fighting the Taliban.
And I think that is the heart of what we need to deal with here, hunting down people
who are criminals.
This is something which the U.S. law enforcement is very well capable of doing and doing while
preserving fundamental civil rights.
And in some ways that's the easiest part of the problem.
The difficult part of the problem is affecting the environment within which violent elements
otherwise would be able to thrive.
So now please allow me to unzip a couple of things here.
First of all, I'm stuck on what happened at Torah Bora.
And this son of a bitch is saying that everything that I said was right.
First of all, there were only 400 al-Qaeda guys in the country at the time as Cynthia Storer,
former CIA officer, maybe an old friend of yours, I don't know, confirmed to me on this show.
And then he says, even then, he says it, even at the seeming height of the crisis immediately
after 9-11, al-Qaeda was a side project.
We decided to go after the Taliban instead.
Okay, so there's that and I want to let you talk about that for 20 minutes if you want.
But then there's the other whole thing where he's not even talking about that.
He's just making a stupid metaphor.
And he's saying that the guys that bum-rushed the capital are al-Qaeda.
And the American right are the Taliban.
Yes.
What the hell?
So talk about the first part first though, man, please.
Yeah.
You know, when I was on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee staff, we had Grignet testify and
we had the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and I forget who the third person was.
But Senator Jean Chahine, a Democrat from New Hampshire, asked a question and it was
very direct and very pointed.
She said, and this was in the spring of 2009, how many members of al-Qaeda are
in Pakistan?
Easy question, direct question.
The answer was 25.
So by 2009, there were 25 members of al-Qaeda in Pakistan.
We set out to destroy al-Qaeda in October of 2001.
And man, they were destroyed.
So what were we still doing there?
What we were doing there was the dawn of the Pakistani terror war.
That was when Obama and the CIA were just starting the drone war there.
Just starting.
We hadn't even had yet debates over refueling the drones, for example, in Baluchistan that
became so controversial.
You're exactly right.
So we decided that we were going to pick a fight, essentially, with the Taliban, with
which we had never had a beef, right?
Well, we didn't have diplomatic relations with them, but we don't have diplomatic
relations with a lot of countries.
Well, in Bill Clinton's government, I mean, you were in the CIA at the time, right?
Isn't it not the case that Bill Clinton supported the rise of the Taliban?
Absolutely, absolutely, because the Taliban were anti-communist.
They were anti-Russian.
And yeah, I mean, it was good for our sphere of influence.
And so this is just five years later, right?
Bill Clinton and the Saudis and the Pakistanis helped them take Kabul in 1996.
So this is five years later, we're pretending like I don't know these guys.
In fact, let's pretend that the Taliban knocked the towers down while we're
letting bin Laden go.
I mean, he even used the word primarily immediately after 9-11.
Our primary objective was to go after the guys that didn't do it and let the
guys who did do it get away.
John, that is exactly what happened.
That is exactly what happened.
happen. Grignet writes in this New York Times piece, and this is exactly what you said a
moment ago, overrepresented among the ranks of angry but ordinary citizens who stormed
the Capitol on January 6th were others, hardly ordinary, committed to violent extremism,
the Proud Boys, the Three Percenters, the Oath Keepers, Christian national chauvinists,
white supremacists, and QAnon fantasists, among others. Okay, listen, all those groups are
nuts. I agree. All those groups are nuts, they're all extremists. But who says that they were
committed to violent extremism? I'd like to see what his sources are for that.
Right, or that they oppose a threat to the American legal order at all. Right, I mean,
is there a 3% or caucus in one state house out of 50 in this country? No. Come on.
Ridiculous. Ridiculous. And like I say, what I said in my own piece is I've known Grignet for
many, many years, decades. And this is CIA code words for using violence, extra judicial violence
against Americans. Hey, y'all, Scott here. If you want a real education in history and
economics, you should check out Tom Woods's Liberty Classroom. Tom and a really great group
of professors and experts have put together an entire education of everything they didn't
teach you in school but should have. Follow through from the link in the margin at scotthorton.org
for Tom Woods's Liberty Classroom. Look here, you and I both know that what you
need is some libertarian institute things, like shirts and sweatshirts and mugs and
stickers to put on the back of your truck and to give to your friends too that say libertarian
institute on them so that everyone will know the origins of your oppositional defiant disorder
and where they can listen to all the best podcasts. So here's what you do. Go to libertosbella.com
and look at all the great libertarian institute stuff they've got going there. Find the
ad in the right hand margin at libertarianinstitute.org.
Libertosbella.com. Okay, so what are they really thinking? Okay, so here's another part of this
thing that they talk about in the interview is he says, and this is just great. You
know this guy for decades, you explain this to me then, translate this for me Kiriakou.
He says, here's an important element we haven't talked about is what I refer to
as insurgent leadership. The fact of the matter is that the most violent elements that we
are concerned about right now see former President Trump as a broadly popular and charismatic
symbol. He is their charismatic leader, whether he chooses to acknowledge it or not. You
know, just as I saw in the Middle East, that the air went out of violent demonstrations
when Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein was defeated and seemed to be defeated. I think the same
situation applies here. The fact of the matter is that Mr. Trump has lost. It's very important
that people see that he has lost is a private citizen. But I think it's extremely important
that his potency as a symbol for the most violent among us is somehow addressed. In
other words, we're to somehow perceive Donald Trump as sitting at Mar-a-Lago leading a continuing
insurgency against the Biden government and an attempt to overthrow it. But we haven't
heard a peep from him. And he hasn't said a word after he hasn't put up any kind of
actual fight of any substance since January 7th. That was the end of that as far
as that goes. And then again, with the analogies here, remember that time, John Kiriakou, that
they captured Saddam Hussein and then the next day America defeated the Sunni-based insurgency
because they gave up? Is that how you remember the year 2004, 2006 and 2007 and 2008?
You know, that is not how I remember it happening. And he knows better. You know,
Bob Drenier is a very smart guy, and he likes to bill himself as the consummate moderate. But
I want to reread what you just said here. Mass demonstrations in Pakistan in support
of Osama bin Laden fell into dull quiescence when he was driven into hiding after September
11th. To blunt the extremists, Mr. Trump's veneer of invincibility must similarly be
crushed. Now, to me, Scott, that that means to take him out. You know, take him out however
you want to politically, legally, judicially, whatever. But some people are going to read
that as just taking him out, if you know what I mean.
Okay. So now, so what is going through these people's head that they're, they must
be just pretending to believe that Donald Trump is about to what? Raise up a brown shirt army
to overthrow all the governors of America and take over the country or something? Give
me a break with this stupidity. This isn't even a comic book.
Well, it says a lot that as soon as this thing was published, John Brennan just jumped
right into the fray on a in an interview on NPR saying that Bob Drenier is, you
know, a genius and brilliant. And this was a brilliantly written piece. And we need to
stop Donald Trump. And he's a danger to the Republic and all the usual garbage that John
Brennan spouts. This was the plan. I mean, Greg and Brennan have been friends for 35 years.
So of course, Brennan was going to come out and take a cheap shot at Trump. That's what
we saw happen. But the scary thing is, you know, a lot of people in the CIA believe
this kind of thing. They believe that they're smarter than everybody else. They're smarter
than you are. They're smarter than I are than I am. And they are going to they're going
to put this out there in the newspaper of record for all the world to see. And they're
going to show how the how the deep state is going to make this whole thing right.
I mean, but at the same time, they're tapping his phone and they know he ain't
doing a damn thing. So this is all just make believe Donald Trump. And look, if
let's say Donald Trump was trying to get real brave right now, all they have to do is send
your replacement down there to have a meeting with him where, hey, now that you're a
private citizen again, you think we were hard on you when we were framing you for
treason with Russia will cut your throat. Shut up. They'd say that right to his
face and he would say, OK, I get it. Maybe that's already happened, right? I
mean, there's he's not doing anything. I guess it's possible he could run again
for the nomination and election under our laws in another four years. But other
than that, I think it's completely ridiculous. What's he going to do? He's
going to see South Florida with what armed force? You know, what are we talking
about? Donald Trump is like David Koresh is about to march on downtown Waco and
sees it. No, he's not sitting at home when you guys showed up.
He is more concerned right now about the Palm Beach City Council asking him to
leave than he is about any kind of insurrection or or raising a standing
army to attack Michigan or, you know, whatever it else he's being he's
being accused of doing right now. OK, but so here's the thing. These guys know
they're lying. This isn't about Trump. This is about picking on the right.
It's about kicking the right wing off of the Internet. And as John Brennan
said, even libertarians. Oh, yeah. Which libertarians ever insulted John Brennan?
I don't know. I'm sorry, guys, if I got us all in trouble. I saw. I chuckled
when I read that. Yeah, well, it's not that funny really. And, you know,
antiwar.com has already been deranged by Google. They rounded us up with
the worst of the right and the left from their point of view back a few
years ago. And they've kicked some of our best allies completely off of
Facebook and Twitter and all kinds of things. And it seems like it's
really only just starting here. But here's let me go ahead and get kind of
kooky on you a minute here for just a second. This is the CIA and you're they
say former CIA, John. I don't know. That's the law. They put you in prison.
I'm pretty sure if there's a former CIA officer, you're one of them. You and
Ray. OK, but so aren't aren't you guys sick and evil and devious enough
that this is all deliberate? Because in fact, you're not just trying to
kick not you. They are not just trying to kick the right wing off the
Internet. They're trying to turn them into a radicalized force. They're
trying to make things worse. They're being provocative because they're
trying to radicalize the right to have more and more of an excuse to
crack down on them. Yes, that's exactly what we're seeing here. You
know, it's funny to me that that the Democrats think that they're
ascendant right now. And so they're overreacting just like so many of
us predicted that they would. But the thing is, this this is always
cyclical and it's going to come back and bite them. And then they're
going to be delisted and then they're going to be thrown off of Twitter
and Facebook and Instagram. And they're going to jump up and down
and say how unfair it is and how un-American it is. And then
we're back where we started again. Yeah, I mean, assuming
someone can find their way around Silicon Valley and all their
restrictions now. I mean, it sort of seems like no, we're
actually a few miles down the slippery slope from where we were
before. In fact, someone interviewing me yesterday said,
doesn't it seem like yeah, for those of us, you're a little
bit older than me, but for those of us who grew up in the 70s, 80s,
90s and even 2000s that that America's over. There's a whole
different era now. Our internet, what we thought the internet
would be, for example, which looks kind of wide open space of
blogs and retweets and whatever you got is becoming
much more like a Chinese style internet and they're going for it.
And in the name of this, the danger of the white supremacist,
which is apparently the right half
of all of American political culture.
And it's very dangerous.
It's very dangerous when,
and in the meantime, we've got these people
like Bob Grenier and like James Clapper
and John Brennan and these other former intelligence people
coming out and professing to be the moderates,
the right thinkers, the ones who are going to protect us
and save us.
And if anything, they're causing damage to the constitution.
And you know what's hilarious about all this?
Is this, I don't know about the role of Grenier here,
but I know that John Brennan was the leading backer
of Jabot al-Nusra in Syria.
Absolutely right. This guy's idea of,
right-wing radical terrorism is we ought to help these guys
shoot some tow missiles at some tanks
and see what kind of money and guns and breakfast
and training and whatever else we can give them
so they can fight better.
Yes, absolutely right.
We can't forget that it was John Brennan
who decided to ally the CIA with al-Qaeda,
which just changed its name to Jabot al-Nusra in Syria.
We were actually fighting on the side of al-Qaeda,
if you can imagine such a thing.
Yep.
Thanks to John.
And this is the same guy talking about
how you're a traitor and I'm a traitor.
Right.
And every, and you know what?
This is exactly what happened after Oklahoma City, right?
The Pactcon operation, which one way or the other,
it's not definitive, so I won't go out on a limb.
It may have been a deliberate provocation.
In fact, I guess I should ask you what you know about that,
but there was Andre Strossmeyer,
seems like he was not really a Nazi.
He was a cop infiltrating this group
and helping provoke them.
And then they did the Oklahoma bombing.
They blamed it on one or two guys
and let the rest get away.
And then they blamed the entire right.
First of all, it was actual Nazis that did it,
but then they pretended that they ignore
the actual Nazis, the literal individual men
who were Nazis who did it.
And instead, they pretended that all militias are Nazis
and smeared all militias that had grown up after Waco
in response to the Waco massacre.
That you're not gonna do that around here.
We'll show you kind of thing.
And they said, no, no, no, these guys all worship Hitler
and hate Jews and kill babies now
after the Oklahoma City bombing.
And they essentially accused Rush Limbaugh,
who to me is the center right.
The absolute, not very far right at all.
And it was Rush Limbaugh and everybody to the right of him.
Every white man in America owns a gun,
did the Oklahoma bombing and slaughtered those babies.
And Bill Clinton bragged,
the Oklahoma bombing saved my presidency
as everybody rallied around and support the flag
and lay a wreath in memory of the people.
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.
So, you can see how dangerous this kind of thing goes
where they wanna try.
I mean, it's just like
with the Muslim terrorist entrapments too, right?
There's been, Trevor Aronson has documented,
there's been between 250 and 300 outright entrapment cases
by the FBI of mostly harmless idiot Muslims in America.
Loners, people with sick mothers
in desperate need of money
and whatever trapped into saying the wrong thing on tape
and locked in jail.
And they can do that same kind of thing.
In fact, the new law that they're proposing, John,
what I read of it, the only thing that it did,
I don't think it created any new crimes that I saw,
at least the version of the bill I saw,
said what it does is it creates a new domestic terrorism
agency inside the Department of Homeland Security
and inside the FBI.
Permanent new agencies to focus on the radical right,
which is, again, the entire right.
That's been discussed since the early 1990s.
On my very first trip to London as a CIA officer,
I'd been to London many times, of course,
but in my first trip as a CIA officer,
we talked with MI5 about their duties
as a domestic intelligence service.
MI6 is famously the foreign intelligence service.
MI5 does only domestic intelligence.
They don't have the power to arrest,
but they don't need to arrest anybody.
That's what Scotland Yard is for.
And the discussions way back then,
I mean, this must have been 1992 or 1993,
we were talking about setting a similar thing up
in the United States, either parallel to the FBI
or as a part of the FBI
that would just spy on American citizens
and then provide that intelligence to the FBI
to affect arrests.
And here we are all these years later,
30 years later,
and it looks like it's gonna come to pass.
And then, but so, yeah, again, it seems like a step.
Back to Cynthia Storer, the former CIA analyst
who I interviewed on the show.
We were talking about radical Islam and such.
And she said that, you know, she essentially confirmed
that what she called the CIA's framework for terrorism,
for understanding terrorism, what causes it
and how to prevent it and how to short-circuit it
and all these things.
It doesn't include religion at all.
Religion is Islam, the Mohammed,
all that has nothing to do with it whatsoever.
She said it's disenfranchised people
who feel like they have tried everything
and there's no accountability and no redress
and their voice is silenced and they're really pissed
and then they resort to, if they're crafty about it,
not just violent revenge attacks,
but attacks designed to provoke political reactions
and move change forward one way or the other,
sometimes into deep chaos before we get
where we're going or this kind of thing.
But that's what it is.
And she was talking, I think she was sort of,
I don't even think she explicitly talked,
maybe she was referring to Assad at the time,
that Assad really could have nipped this thing
in the bud a lot better if he'd been a lot nicer,
which I'm not sure I believe that
because there was so much foreign intervention going on,
it was too late for his ass anyway
and I think he knew that too.
But she was saying, people were just coming out
protesting and then they got met with real hard violence
and then they really reacted badly to that
and then it's a cycle of violence
but whether we're talking about Syria,
whether the CIA's intervening
or whether we're talking about anywhere else,
that's basically how it goes.
So then I'm saying if these guys have all read
the same framework that she's read,
then this seems like early steps
in trying to create a crisis,
trying to provoke some kind of massive violent conflict
that'll lead us to what at the end?
I mean, it's like they're gonna be able to outlaw
the right wing party in America or something like that
and suspend elections from now on
and force us all to submit to Kamala Harris
under the new order or something.
So if that's right, that they're reading
that same framework the same way
and we're on a John Brennan plan
for implementing this thing and making matters
worse deliberately in the shorter medium term,
to what end?
Other than just, oh good,
we get to have a new agency and exercise some more power
which is fun and cash checks
and not have to get real jobs, I understand that.
But do they have something in mind
for what America's supposed to look like
after the end of four or eight years of this or worse?
You know, I don't think they do.
I think that for them, the end game is power and authority
and all that matters to them
is that they remain in charge when this is all over
and what you do, one of the things
that they taught us, Scott at the CIA
and from my first week on the job,
I learned this little bit of office politics,
is that in order to make yourself as important
as you possibly can,
you have to constantly work at expanding your realm, right?
You've got to be the king of as many people as possible.
And so people, managers at the CIA
were constantly trying to expand their authority.
But when you get up to that level,
that senior level of the John Brennan's
and the Bob Grenier's and you want to expand your authority,
that expands then into other agencies.
I remember in 2002, John Brennan was in a feud
with Jim Pabot, it was the deputy director for operations.
I worked for Jim Pabot and Brennan wanted
to be more important than he was.
He had been the deputy executive director.
And so they created this new organization
that at the time was called the TTIK,
the Transnational Terrorism Information Center.
It became the National Counterterrorism Center.
And Brennan was the first head.
Well, he wanted the TTIK to break off from the CIA
and to become its own agency.
So he could be the first head
of this new intelligence agency.
Not for any other reason,
not because it would have streamlined the information,
the analysis would have been any better,
just because he wanted to be in charge of his own little.
fight them. And Pavitt blocked that. Well, as it turned out then, Brennan was the only
person in 2008 from the CIA to join the Obama campaign. Everybody else either went to Hillary
or to McCain. And when Obama won the election, Brennan was able to call his own shot. He
became the deputy national security advisor and then the CIA director. And then until the
Biden campaign, I mean, he was telling everybody in Washington who would listen that he wanted
to be the secretary of defense. The only reason he didn't become secretary of defense was
because Biden was committed to elevating women and minorities into these senior positions.
So it's all about power. It's all about individual authority. It's all about being as important
as you can possibly be in Washington. And the American people be damned this whole time.
If that ain't the theme of the 21st century, I don't know what is. That never even enters
the conversation. Yeah, like that. Not even be damned, but just not even brought up
to be damned. Yep. Yep. That's it. By the way, you're in the CIA during the 90s. Tell
me what you guys know. Tell me what you know about the Oklahoma bombing from back then,
John. Anything? No, not a not a single thing. Not a single thing. Of course, I was overseas
at the time. I was stationed in Bahrain at the time. But but this was this was
as great a FBI fuck up as, you know, as there's ever been in American history.
You got that right. Got that right. We got a book coming out. I'm not writing it. I'll
be proud to write the introduction to it. A new fellow at the Libertarian Institute,
Richard Booth, who's put together the ultimate Oklahoma City bombing document archive
at Oklahoma at Libertarian Institute.org slash OKC, by the way. He's writing a book about it
that I think is going to be the masterpiece. And that's going to be we're going to be
publishing that this year. So that is great. All right. Well, listen, thank you so much
for your time. I'm sorry I'm late. I'm supposed to be talking with Danny right
now. But thank you so much for coming back on the show. I really appreciate it. And
listen, please stay focused on this and writing. I know that you understand how
important it is that you have former CIA officer after your name and that that means
that you can get people to listen to you on a little bit higher level. And it is important
as you recognize and as you've already taken the lead in doing, you get right out
there and say, I contradict my former friend here. Absolutely not. It's so
important to counter this narrative with people like yourself on your level of
credential in media terms, you know. Thank you, man. I appreciate that very
much. Oh yeah. Thanks, John. Appreciate it. Thanks. You take care.
All right, you guys, that's John Kiriakou. He is at consortiumnews.com.